foreign
[Music]
game
we are 8 27
and I remind those of you watching on
YouTube that the sort of
point of the speedrun is to emphasize
openings
I will be playing exclusively my
recommended repertoire
obviously when we climb a little bit
higher
we will be focused more on developing
opening Theory
and this is just sort of the the
companion speed run to my official
opening recommendations
okay this time we're White against Alon
art k k let's go one to E4
uh for those watching on YouTube the
reason my rating is now 911 I just want
a three move game where our opponent
abandoned
all right
let's go might have three
well actually I mean
my Like official recommendation is the
Vienna
um but I basically have two like there's
two openings that I recommend for you to
learn uh against D4 E5 there's the
Vienna and as you guys know from the
previous speedrun the four night Scotch
which sounds like a really boring
opening but if you watch the previous
Speed Run carefully you will know that
it's an incredibly dangerous weapon at
every level under 2000 and even over two
thousand it's a totally legitimate line
it just has this reputation as you know
one of those like oh it's just like a
four nights you know you're just like
you know the most mundane development
but it it's won us a lot of quick games
94 what the heck is this yeah this is
this is the kind of move that is
intended to scare you know scare a
beginner oh Knight is moving into the
center but if you just look at it
carefully you will see uh that it just
wanders upon it I mean I don't I'm not
familiar with this move maybe this is
some sort of trick Gambit
but I don't buy it so you know what's
funny is that if you were afraid to take
the pawn on E5 right you could also just
keep developing with Bishop C4
like you don't have to react to this
Knight on D4 at all but obviously here
like we just take the bottom E5 like
that there's nothing to calculate here
and there's nothing to calculate because
black has nothing developed so so if you
think logically like there cannot be a
trick when your opponent has like one
developed piece that's not the way the
chest Works Knight F6
but we're not satisfied just winning the
pawn
the the sort of Soviet Schoolboy
approach here would be to drop the
Knight back to F3 and smoke the night
out of D4
but I think
well I think we can play a lot more
opportunistically
um I think we can play a lot more
opportunistically if we wanted to with
Bishop C4 the funny thing is that after
Bishop C4
there is a move which quite concerns me
believe it or not
after Bishop C4 there is this weird move
Queen d8 to E7
and you might look at this and say I
don't get that move at all like
you know we can just take on F7 but as
I'll show you guys after the game uh I
think we've transposed to a weird trick
line
where white is in fact much better but
there's quite a bit of theory there
so I think much safer and much more
prudent is just to say hey this Knight
on E5 is quite vulnerable right why is
it vulnerable isn't he isn't it in the
center isn't that a good thing well just
a piece being in the center I've
explained this before does not
necessarily make it good right the 995
lacks lacks an anchor
and it's vulnerable to attack by several
different pieces Queen to E7 is the main
threat because not only will it chase
the Knight back it would then allow
black to recapture the pawn on e4
so the simplest way to play is just to
double back to F3
and this kills two birds with one stone
because not only do we move the Knight
we also contest the Knight on D4 which
our opponent just immediately blunders
in one move Knight takes D4 thank you
very much for the minor piece
and the game is already over so
and now I know the YouTube comments are
going to be like okay you know why is it
that when you play you know you're
playing these people who just like
blunder pieces on every move but but
it's it's I think a large part of it is
because of the our choice of openings
okay do you take C4 let's focus on
converting this Advantage clinically
okay
so in this position I think a lot of
people at the at a beginner level would
be very tempted
would be very tempted by the move Bishop
F1 to B5 check let's develop our Bishop
with Tempo that is not a good move why
is Bishop B5 check not a good move
and
if you're watching on on YouTube you
know make sure that you're answering
along with the chat C6 yeah Bishop B5
allows C6 and then in that position you
might say I see a tactic there's Knight
D4 takes C6
but after BC Bishop takes C6 check black
brings the bishop out to D7
you take the rook in the corner and
black recaptures the bishop and what you
have then is an extra exchange and two
pawns white is still winning but there's
absolutely no need to give away two of
your minor pieces much simpler is just
to drop the snipe back to B3
and the reason I'm dropping it back to
P3
is because of process of elimination
it's not this is such a nice Square I
don't want to bring it up to B5 because
that just walks right into A6 I
definitely don't want to bring it back
to E2 because it blocks the development
of the bishop and right now the most
important thing for us is to develop our
pieces rapidly and actively okay C5 this
move accomplishes exactly nothing it
doesn't threaten anything because the C4
square is protected by our light squared
Bishop and here of course there are
multiple ways that we could proceed with
our development
are I think top priorities here of
course are to complete the development
of our King side number one but number
two this Pawn on e4 is very annoying
yeah it's hanging over our position it's
making it a little bit hard for us to
breathe so what move comes immediately
to mind yeah I think we should just play
the move D3 let's get rid of that pawn
on e4
in order to make it easier for us to
coordinate our minor pieces and also to
move D3 is Good from a developmental
standpoint because it opens up the dark
squared Bishop which we could later
deploy for example to G5
okay
so you might say but we're not
developing a piece well the thing is we
don't really need to be developing a
piece on every move we're perfectly safe
here Queen E7
so again there's like a million ways
that we could play here but anytime I
see the alignment of the queen and the
King
that is usually a liability rather than
a uh a a
what's the opposite of liability it's
liability rather than a strength I guess
and it's a liability for two reasons the
first is that if you just look at
Black's King on E8
asset asset thank you yeah it's a
liability rather than an asset that's
the word I was looking for that King 98
is totally out of squares well you might
say it's not out of squares but if the
White Queen controls the D file the
black thing is out of squares couple
that with the fact that black has
already advanced C5 what does that tell
me well that tells me that if we deliver
a check on B5 with the with the bishop
black is no longer going to have the
move C6 so what move am I heavily
implying that we should play
right but we need to be able to control
the D file we want to create the thread
of a devastating check on B5 potentially
yeah just D takes C4
I think a lot of people would be afraid
of Knight takes even black sets up a
discovery but all of that is a total
paper tiger even if we didn't have
Bishop B5 check which wins on the spot
after Knight takes C4 at the very least
we could just take the Knight and then
block with our Queen and force a queen
trade right Bishop F5 okay well that's
probably a better move actually than
Knight takes E4
but it doesn't change our approach
obviously the bishop is Untouchable
because the black queen
pins the E4 Pawn
but the simplest of course is just to
play Bishop two B5 check we continue our
development with tempo
yeah Bishop B5 is very natural and then
we can just castle and then we can just
Castle
again something that I repeat every time
we're early on in the speed run which is
that when you're up a piece like this
there's usually going to be like four or
five moves in every position that are
approximately equivalent in strength so
you might be looking at this and saying
well hey I like the move F3 why didn't
he play the move F3 to defend the E4
Pawn well F3 is a perfectly reasonable
working man's move nothing wrong with
the move F3 I just think Bishop B5 is a
little bit more to the point
okay Bishop D7
well I think we should just trade I
think we should just trade let's get
that Bishop off the board
and we are also trying to force black to
recapture with the Knight which is going
to give us this incredibly beautiful
stronghold on D5 for our nine right
okay and we don't need to play F3 our
Pawn on e4 is perfectly well protected
okay Queen takes D7 and without even
thinking twice
without even thinking twice we trade
Queens
but just because we've traded Queens
does not mean
that it is time to abandon basic
principles right we have not completed
our development so let's focus on doing
that now
I'm thinking here that rather than
Castle in kingside I think it's a better
idea for us to try to Castle queenside
right there's no longer any risk
associated with gasoline Queen side
and the benefit of castling queenside is
that we simultaneously bring our Rook
onto a very juicy open file now what
needs to happen in order for us to cast
Queen side well we need to get this
bishop out well where should we put this
bishop you might say well let's put it
on no not H6 let's put it on G5 because
that's the most active Square it's not
the most active score Bishop G5 just
walks right into F6 or H6 so the the
next best thing is just to play Bishop
C1 to F4 this bishop is invulnerable on
F4 it's also controlling the D6 Square
making it harder for black to develop
his Bishop okay C4 whatever
now anytime a pawn is pushed a square is
going to be opened up right you should
get into the Habit even as a beginner of
always asking yourself when a pawn is
pushed what squares are now available to
your pieces and applying this logic
directly you can see that you have this
juicy nice Square in the center for your
knight that has just been opened up and
if black plays Bishop f8 to C5 then we
can still Castle Queen side because the
Rook is going to be protecting the
Knight
and it's simple moves of course Knight
A5 is also good yeah the more advanced
players are going to see them move
Knight B3 to A5 for King the B7 and C4
pawns but Knight T4 is even simpler and
right now we're focused on
keeping it simple castles Queen side
defending the Knight with our Rook
defending the night with our Rook
we don't need even to attack any more
pawns we don't really need to seek out
any further material what we need to do
here is bring all of our pieces into the
game and eventually we're going to crash
through down the D file okay so I
mentioned this phrase crash through down
the D file what does that really mean
well what that really means is we're
going to pile up our Rooks on the D file
we're going to move the Knight away from
D4 and we're going to orchestrate a
bunch of trades on the D file that's
going to make the win a lot easier so
how are we going to do that well for
starters I like to move Rook to D2
preparing to double Rooks on the D file
we don't need to move this Knight just
yet we can just keep it on D4
now hopefully as you're watching this my
strategy is making sense you should be
sort of saying I can see why he's doing
what he's doing even if you would have
chosen a slightly different method in
your own conversion right you could you
can convert the way that you feel
there's different styles of converting a
big Advantage like this
but the goal is for this to be making
you know easy logical sense Knight F6
does this create any threats no it does
not because the E4 Pawn for the moment
is defended by our Knight we can
continue with our plan completing the
doubling of the Rooks
and of course if black plays the move
Rook FTE then I think would be a perfect
opportunity for us to play F3 yeah let's
play F3 uh to protect the four Pawn once
and for all so that we don't have to
worry about Knight takes E4
everything is solid everything is safe
and on the next move
we are going to move this Knight off of
D4 opening up the D file for the Rooks
and for example after you play the move
Knight to F5 which is the ideal Square
for the Knight you might notice okay
Knight H5 never mind forget it
um that's a good move actually that is a
good move it it harasses it harasses the
bishop on F4
but the bishop has of course the nice
little E3 Square
let's see if our opponent finds him with
F5 I'll be very impressed if he finds F5
I'll be very impressed if he finds F5
because that's a super Advanced move
okay B5 yeah B5 is
is not is not effective
uh it's not effective because it simply
blunders upon obviously we don't want to
take with this Knight because that would
plunder the bishop with a pin but if we
wanted to really stick to our strategy
we could also play the move Knight to F5
here we don't even really need uh to
take any further Pawns
and in fact I'm going to show you guys
how effective this strategy can be let's
just go Knight F5 here I don't care
about this additional Pawn we are
already up a piece in a pawn and as I've
mentioned in previous speed runs there
is the sort of law of diminishing
returns of material the more
extra material you have the less
meaningful additional pawns and
additional material because so right if
you're up a pawn winning a second Pawn
is massive that's a game changer if
you're up a piece then winning a second
piece often doesn't actually change the
evaluation because you're waiting to
begin with okay G6 is
is
um
accelerates the the defeat we can just
play Bishop takes Bishop simultaneously
attacking The Rook on f8
and that the game is over
and the game is over
game is over
yeah
I think it's likely that our opponent
will resign here
yeah simple a simple game that was made
anti-climactic by the fact that our
opponent blundered a piece in the
opening we take the Rook on f8
okay but but I would caution you again
saying this was not a worthy opponent
everybody
um you were once at this level too so
the last thing we want is to make people
feel embarrassed that they are just
starting to play
the whole point of the speed run is to
give everybody something to learn from
wherever they are in their chess Journey
what should we do now again how do we if
we want to stick to our strategy of like
maximum simplification what should we do
yeah
trade the Rooks right it's going to be
so much easier once the Rooks are off
the board
yeah this is over Rook d8 just drift now
you might say well why didn't we take
the pawn of course taking the pawn is
also fine but I'm just trying to
illustrate this idea that trading and
simplifying it really often is the
simplest way to win these positions okay
now we can do a bill in a billion
different things but I think the
simplest is just to play the move G2 to
G3 chasing the Knight off of f4
obviously though the pawn was hanging so
just defending with Tempo that's all
we're doing we're chasing the night away
notice that yeah I was about to say E2
is protected literally and of course our
opponent puts the Knight there
and now it's really easy FeFe
and to win such a position
in the in the quickest possible way yeah
the easiest is to use your extra
material to win a bunch of Pawns and
then make a bunch of Queens like rather
than trying to checkmate with the rook
in the Knight use the Rook to win like
upon and create a pass spawn
basically just make a queen
and the simplest way to do that is of
course to go after the A6 pawn and the
way to do that is by Rook play playing
Rook D6
and Rook D6 we're going to go after the
spawn then we're going to create a
passer let's drop it back to D5
skewering the pawns here
sounds very pedantic that I'm talking
about what to do here
but if you really want to improve you
should try to convert every aspect of
the game into a learning experience
which you can do
okay now of course we can try to win
both of these pawns let's go Rook Rook
before Rook A5 doesn't matter
okay whatever just I mean you can take
with a pond you can take with a knight
we'll take with a pawn because that
already creates a past Pawn
and now one last teachable moment folks
um the easiest way here is to play the
move Rook to D4 to cut off the black
king and when I say this word cut off
what that means is you occupy a file and
obviously the king without the
assistance of any other pieces is unable
to cross that file and this is very
effective if you're trying to promote a
pawn because now you can close your eyes
and you can just push the C pun forward
and notice that the Knight is also
defending the roxo the king is utterly
helpless
now if you're a beginner you would never
want to pre-move in such a position you
want to spend at least a couple of
seconds per move to make sure that
you're not stalemating your appointment
and now the simplest is Ladder Checkmate
so the King has one Escape Square which
is G6 so let's drop our Queen back to F5
to cover that escape square and pave the
way for a check on D7 which is going to
drive the king back to the eighth rank
which is precisely the fastest way to
Checkmate always to drive the king onto
the bottom rank
check Queen defends The Rook
and easy clap check
King f8 and mate on F7 we didn't even
use our Knight
good stuff
okay that was an easy simple game
and Buckle in because a lot of the games
that we play like probably the next 10
15 games are going to be pretty
straightforward and will probably be
decided by like one move blunders but
that's okay that doesn't mean you can't
learn from them
so again here we can see
here we can see the fact that a lot of
these games are just decided by poor
opening play this blunders the pawn on
E5 but
since this speed run
has an emphasis on the opening let's
talk a little bit about why I rejected
the move Bishop to C4 so what's
interesting about this move
is that I actually am familiar with the
line that goes Bishop C4 now there is
the move Knight D4 this move does exist
it's not a good move but it exists
and after Knight takes C5 the point is
to play the move Queen E7 and
surprisingly things actually get quite
tricky here because if you play Knight
takes F7
black has a very nasty little move here
and it's not Knight take C4 who can tell
me why Knight takes C4 loses on the spot
what should white do in this position
why does it move after which blackened
virtually resign what is it
that would bite seem that black has all
sorts of threats on the e-file yeah just
get out of their castles just Castle
kingside
yeah just get out of there and that's it
let me look at Black's position The Rook
is hanging the E file is black is just
going to get massacred down the E file
and if black plays Knight C3 then you
simultaneously recapture and attack the
Knight black simply cannot keep
everything protected at the same time if
Rook G8 then the simplest is just Knight
takes E4 again alignment of queen and
king always watch for that in the
opening
and that's it
so instead black has this move D5 yes
and this intercepts the bishop and the
Knight
so if you play Knight takes D5 black can
actually grab the Knight on F7 and you
don't have any effective discoveries
Knight takes C7 Queen takes E7
if Knight takes F6 Queen takes F6 so
when you're calculating a discovered
check or discovered attack make sure
that the piece you're trying to win
cannot itself recapture uh and get out
of the discovered attack right this is a
classic scenario
yeah you can play them of Knight B6 here
but but don't miss the forest for the
trees whites King is now all alone on E1
black and Slide the queen up to G6
and The Rook on A8 is the least
significant of all of the pieces on the
board black plays Queen takes G2 and
this is actually a pretty famous type of
trick if you go Rook F1 Queen takes C4
leads to Checkmate Bishop B2 Knight F3
those of you who've watched like your
share of Eric Rosen videos will know
that this is actually a classic pattern
in the Italian
and of course the most famous
instantiation of this is the Blackburn
gamut Bishop C4 and again this move
Knight D4
and I have seen a gazillion Scholastic
games that go Knight takes F7 Queen
takes G2 Rook F1 takes Bishop B2 and
Knight F3 Checkmate Super Famous this is
the sh not the yeah the Blackburn
chilling again but yeah of course this
is totally on sound
and here I can just play Knight takes D4
castles and get a big Advantage the
spawn is terrible
but it's a good opening
for for a couple of laws so after 95
Knight F6 Bishop C4 Queen E7 Knight F7
we were considering the move D5 now you
might say well I can just take the rook
in the corner but after DC you get a
classic scenario where black has already
won one minor piece and black is most
probably going to win the nine on h8
because it is no way back white is still
better here but it's very complicated
and this is totally contrary to what
we're trying to illustrate in the
speeder and I'm trying to play Simple
Chess at least for the first like 15-20
games
and finally if you play the move Bishop
takes F7 check then after King d8 white
is in trouble
why is white in trouble because the
Knight is hanging why is that a problem
well if tonight moves then The Bishop's
going to be hanging classic scenario the
queen attacks both pieces and if you
play F4 to support the Knight then black
chases the Knight away with a pawn and
white actually loses a piece here and
loses the game
so for this reason we just dropped our
Knight back to F3 it's simple it's
strong and it's easy to calculate and
obviously this just blenders a piece in
one move if I were playing Black I would
probably go Bishop to C5 here trying to
trade on my own terms remember that
concept which basically means very often
when you have a situation like this
people just assume either you have to
trade or you have to decline the trade
by moving your piece back but there is a
third option you can say hey I'm willing
to trade but you're gonna have to give
me something in return right in this
case black just simultaneously develops
a piece what's interesting is that the
top engine move here is actually this
incredibly strange move Knight C3 to E2
trying to smoke the Knight out of D4 but
I think the simplest is Bishop E2 just
develop your pieces castles castles and
obviously black has virtually no
compensation for the pawn I mean these
pieces are active but they are not uh
going to give Black full compensation
after rookie 80 can just play D3 and
then Bishop E3 and eventually you're
going to get this Knight out of D4 it's
not going to stay here forever right
it's not going to stay here forever and
maybe black can try D5 get some counter
play going but still this is this is a
pawn down position D5 probably can play
Bishop G5 and black is still in trouble
here Okay so
this would have been the best way to
Garner defensive chances instead black
blunders a piece in one move
now once again
remember that the check on this diagonal
is often overrated by beginners you
should never forget about the fact that
a pawn can block the checks
simultaneously attacking the bishop you
should also not forget that in this
situation the best way for white to
salvage the situation is Knight takes C6
common idea BC Bishop C6 Fork but black
gets the bishop out in order to be able
to recapture and still you should not go
for this if you can keep your extra
piece here your quote unquote only up in
exchange and you've also given up a
pretty important light Square Bishop so
black has like this idea things can kind
of get complicated here
right your pieces are also very
undeveloped so although white is winning
this complicates the winning process by
a lot
does that make sense
so for this reason we are not afraid to
make retreating moves Knight B3
now we identify the main obstacle to
healthy development which in this case
is this E4 Pawn which is kind of hanging
over our position and controlling
important squares so we take it off the
board we play the move D3
and remember you should never be afraid
of a move like Bishop G4 because you can
just block with Bishop B2 do not fear
one moveitis right moves that carry
threats aren't always dangerous
Queen E7 D take C4
and if black had taken with the Knight
we would have thrown in a check on B5
and won a second piece because after
Bishop D7 the queen is what's called
overloaded
and here just like Queen 67 check Bishop
takes D7 and at the end the Knight is
now undefended he can play Knight takes
C4 I guess black and wind the second
then the Beast back with the rookie
eight but still obviously uh one one
extra piece is is more than enough
okay so for this reason our opponent
played Bishop F5 we still played Bishop
E5 check we traded the Bishops we traded
the Queens we got our Bishop out we
brought our Knight into the center we
doubled Rooks on the main open file we
reinforced the E4 Pawn we orchestrated a
trade of Bishops and obviously our
opponent made things a lot easier for us
by committing a further blunder just
last thing folks this move F5 would have
been relatively speaking better
who can explain to me what the point is
like what if white just plays Knight D4
takes F5
this is a good pattern to keep in mind
if you want to generate chances
good pattern to keep in mind
yeah Rook takes F5 Rook takes F5 and
suddenly white is has lost the extra
piece back because if you take the Rook
then Bishop takes E3 pins the the rook
and wins The Exchange back
and if Bishop takes C5 then Rook the
same Rook that was hanging also
recaptures the bishop right Rook takes
you back white is still completely
winning here by the way white is still
completely winning here I mean you're
dominating and you're up two Pawns
but there is no point in allowing this
uh and and the best move for white is
actually just to move the bishop back to
a defended square a common idea and
something you should file away in your
mental Rolodex you move a piece away
from an undefended Square to a defended
Square on the same diagonal right Bishop
D3 to G1 sounds like a typical GM move
but it should make perfect sense to now
Knight takes F5 is actually a threat
and if black plays Fe and you just
recapture with the other Knight and look
at how nicely the knights are positioned
here does that make sense
and that's all she wrote folks after
Knight F5 and Bishop C5 the rest
uh will do without further commentary
because we just traded Rooks in one
easily
hope you enjoyed the speed run guys and
I will definitely put in a stream
tomorrow
thanks again for hanging out and thanks
everybody for the raids see you later
foreign
[Music]